The next library we will cover is the random
library, which provides several ways to generate
random numbers or a random value from a list
of values.
Random numbers play an important role in gaming
as many games need, as part of their flow,
different events to happen each time one plays
those games to keep them fun and interesting.
As we have many random library pieces to cover
in this topic, I won’t worry about making
these relate to gaming in detail but understand
that many games need a randomizer to ask a
random question or position a player in a
random spot.
For any of these random library methods, the
random library needs to be imported, and,
in this 623-random file, that import takes
place on line 1 with the from random statement.
Then, we see that the first method we cover,
randrange, is imported.
A for statement is set on line 2 to run 10
times.
The randrange method returns a number between
the first number in the range and the last
number minus one, just like the second number
in a range for a for statement.
I will run this code and we see 10 numbers
between 5 and 19.
As is the case with for loops, we can add
a step to the random number range.
For example, in a game, one team has all odd
numbers and the other has all even numbers.
I will add a comma and 2 to the randrange
method, rerun the code, and we see all odd
numbers in the result, as the first number
in the range, 5, is odd.
If I change the first number to a six and
rerun the code, the numbers are even because
we ask for random numbers in steps of 2.
The next random library method, randint, returns
an integer between two specified numbers,
and, unlike the randrange method, includes
the last number in the range.
I will change the randrange method to randint
and the content in the parentheses to 1 comma
20.
I will rerun the code, and we see an error
message indicating that randint is not defined?
Why?
What I have done here can be a common occurrence
when we use a library and import a specific
module.
On line 1, the randrange module is being imported.
We need this module to be randint, so I will
make the change, rerun the code, and the code
works perfectly.
Next, let's look at the random method, which
returns a floating point decimal between 0
and 1.
I will change the library module being imported
to random, on line 1.
Then, I will set the print statement to print
the random method to run the method that generates
that floating point number.
I will run this code and we see 10 random
numbers between 0 and 1.
When would we use this type of random number?
We could use this random number to give a
bonus opportunity in a game a percentage of
the time, like 25% of the time.
I will add some logic to this code to indicate
that if the random number is .75 or higher,
to print a message indicating it is bonus
time.
First, I will change line three to store the
random number generated in a variable, since
random by itself is not a variable.
Then, I will add an if statement to see if
the random number, x, is at least .75, meaning
it’s in the highest 25 percent, and add
a print bonus statement.
I will run this code several times, and we
seem to be averaging hitting the bonus twice
to three times per run.